<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-09T08:01:48-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Evangelicals and Trump</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/09/evangelicalism-trump.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evangelicals and Trump" /><published>2020-12-09T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-09T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/09/evangelicalism-trump</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/09/evangelicalism-trump.html">&lt;p&gt;Fighting for our rights&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not serving others&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting Trump in the place of Jesus&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Fighting for our rights</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dealing with Sin in Ministry</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/14/sin-ministry.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dealing with Sin in Ministry" /><published>2020-02-14T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-02-14T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/14/sin-ministry</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/14/sin-ministry.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;incomplete&quot;&gt;INCOMPLETE&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week our Associate Pastor resigned, confessing that he’s been having a sexual relationship with an adult youth group volunteer.  They are both married.  He has four kids.  He was an Elder, part of our church’s (formerly) four-man leadership team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Before I go any further, note that although there are two people involved in this situation, I’m directly speaking to how we handled the man’s part of the responsibility.  This focus is not to diminish the woman’s responsibility or accountability, nor is it to imply that we haven’t spent just as much care and heartache in handling her situation as well.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all devistated.  These two people we love have broken our trust, deceiving us for over a year now.  We feel cheated, foolish, and used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hard part about dealing with this situation is that we Elders have had to deal with this man on three different levels: 1.) as an Employee, 2.) as a fellow Elder, and 3.) as a member under our care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;as-an-employee&quot;&gt;As an Employee&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision on how to deal with this situation with an employee of the church was made simple by this man’s resignation.  However, it should be assumed that he would have been fired immediately, because, as an employer in the least-spiritual sense of the word, we can’t have this going on in our workplace.  This is an issue of integrity and ethics, and this wouldn’t fly in any other workplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;as-a-fellow-elder&quot;&gt;As a Fellow Elder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an emotionally hard hill to climb.  He’s been an integral part of our team: not just because of his administrative and organizational skills, but because we value his insight in decisionmaking.  He genuinely loves Jesus and loves His Church.  He always has, and I will never doubt that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this man’s actions have hurt our people’s trust in their Elders.  You see, we understand this role as that of shepherds: we lead, guide and protect.  We will give an account for our people before Jesus someday, and we’ll be judged more harshly because of the responsibilty that we’ve been entrusted with.  Yet here we are, facing our community with the news that one of us was far from the man of integrity that they trusted us to be.  Futhermore, the rest of us failed to protect them from the results of this.  I’m not sure if this affair was truly preventable, but there were warning signs that we didn’t heed just because this man is a “good guy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were red flags.  When our Senior Pastor called the meeting, us other Elders already knew what it was about. We knew the two of them were good friends, often joking around together and leading youth trips with no other adults along for the ride.  He always passionately defended this volunteer when we had to discuss a couple of issues regarding the woman’s spiritual maturity.  What we didn’t know was the phone calls they had, and we didn’t know that they were meeting alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with his position as an employee, he was removed as an Elder without any need for discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;as-a-church-member&quot;&gt;As a Church Member&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue is much more nuanced than the others.  Where it was obvious what needed to be done with him as an employee and Elder, our approach to dealing with his sin in this case required some discussion. One of us had been his best friend since college – over 20 years, and me and my family have known them for years, with our wives and kids being best friends.  All three of us remaining Elders have teens in the youth group that this man led.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This man is our brother.  He’s walked with us through some tremendous issues in our lives.  He’s been a mentor and friend to our sons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-we-faced-our-community&quot;&gt;How We Faced Our Community&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The staff member resigned/confessed on a Monday evening.  The remaining elders stayed for an initial discussion/debrief.  During this discussion we decided that &lt;strong&gt;we needed to notify our congregation with as much information as possible as soon as possible.  We did this for two reasons: to avoid even the appearance of a cover-up, and also to prevent bad information from being spread.&lt;/strong&gt;  What we discovered later was this early meeting would allow us to set the tone for the congregation: one of grief over anger, and restoration over shunning.  We decided that pre-empting our regular Wednesday night activities would be our best option, as it was a time when the core members of our church were already in the building, plus it was soon enough that we could head off any rumors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday night we Elders met along with our wives to further refine our message, as well as assign roles for Wednesday night (since our Associate Pastor also led the Youth Ministry).  My wife and I volunteered to tell the Youth while the other two elders would explain the situation to the adults.  Children would not be told anything so that their parents could use their judgment in how to explain this to their kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also assigned jobs to personally notifying church leaders (official or otherwise).  In addition to notifying our volunteer childrens’ minister, we also reached out our other adult youth volunteer, and some senior adults that serve as anchors and influencers to our congregation.  These people were either involved in the events of the coming Wednesday or were people who might need to ask detailed questions in private about what happened to better support the congregation through this.  Additionally, this showed these people some respect, that we would trust them with this news in advance of everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, Wendesday night, literally 48 hours after we ourselves got the news, we met with the church.  The other two Elders met with the adults, while me, my wife, and an adult volunteer met with the teenagers. (Naturally, I can only share details about my own experience that night)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[It was like funeral for the students that knew. Hugging, hushed tones]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began by telling the teens that tonight we were going to find out how big they believed Jesus is.  I also led by telling them that I had bad news for them.  With this in mind, I didn’t make them wait long anticipating what the bad news would be.  I did, however, take a moment to explain who I was (for those I didn’t know), as well as our role as Elders.  I said we were shepherds, that we lead, guide, and protect the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I just said it: “[This man] resigned Monday night.  He and [this woman] have been having a sexual affair.”  It was hard, but I wanted to be as direct as possible so there was no misunderstanding about what had been going on.  Also, avoiding ambiguity showed them respect as young adults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a direction in which I wanted to take the meeting, but it required them some time to process the news.  So, I told a story from my own experience about this that might be helpful to those still listening and would also allow others to let the news soak in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, I have been through a similar experience as a teenager.  My wife and I had a youth pastor that moved on to a new position in our city, and within a year he left his wife and two boys for (literally) the new church’s organ player.  In our case, when the teens heard the news, they all scattered.  I know of a woman who will still have nothing to do with Christianity even 25 years later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want this for our teens, especially my own kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told them it was okay to feel whatever they were feeling, even anger.  I told them anger isn’t sinful in and of itself, but it can become sinful.  Also that it feels safe – you feel protected and strong, but it’s corrosive, and bitterness will overwhelm and destroy you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I passed around paper and let them write anonymous questions on them.  After they passed them in, I answered them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One was, “How could they do this to us?”  I said that no one ever wakes up one morning and says, “I think I’m going to destroy my life and all of those around me.”  It’s much more gradual than that.  I told them an abbreviated version of what the Youth Minister told us: it started as phone calls about the ministry, that turned into theological discussions, that led to discussions about their personal lives, that eventually ran out of their control.  Its a slow decline down, not a fast fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone asked how soon they could talk to the spouses and kids involved.  I was getting ready to respond when an adult volunteer spoke up,  She said that she had a miscarriage a few years ago, and that initially people didn’t know what to say, so at best they told her the “If you need anything, just let us know” kind of thing.  She said that before long, she was all alone and felt forgotten.  Even if they didn’t know what to say to her, she just wanted someone to listen, or even to say they were thinking about her.  She said that the teens should reach out as soon as they want, and if they are told that they don’t want to talk, then back off.  Even if they’re not ready to open up, it’s at least nice to know that someone is thinking of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, they asked, “How soon can we show them love?” referring to the youth pastor and the volunteer.  That was a tearjerker.  Of course, I said, “Right now.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out the meeting with the adults went better than we anticipated.  People were hurt and angry, but they kept their heads. They expressed that they wanted to get involved to help fill in the gaps that the associate pastor filled, as well as that they wanted to reach out to the people involved for healing and restoration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an incredible night.  Afterward several of the teens (including my own kids) told me that it went the best that it could have. I know the teens actually left inspired.  They wanted to take ownership of the youth group, to go to work doing ministry to one another and to the rest of the church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interacting-with-the-families-involved&quot;&gt;Interacting with the Families Involved&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the youth’s ministry to others, my boys coordinated with a friend to go to by groceries for the former associate pastor’s family, as they are close friends.  We met with another young man at the grocery store on Saturday morning and went shopping.  They spent their own money to buy fun snacks and candy and chocolate milk and unicorn mac ‘n cheese and Monsters.  We delivered it to the man’s family and spent a while talking with his wife about her situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She is devistated, completely broken and humiliated.  She’d been fooled, and that realization hurt.  Of course, no one holds her responsible for what her husband did (and she knows that!), yet she still feels embarassed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her strongest emotion at the time was anger, and I think that makes a lot of sense.  She’s said repeatedly that he doesn’t really understand the magnitude of what he’s done.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">INCOMPLETE</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Simpler Life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/23/simpler-life.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Simpler Life" /><published>2019-05-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-05-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/05/23/simpler-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/23/simpler-life.html">&lt;p&gt;If I’m not careful, life gets really complicated really fast.  Just the noise of following the news can be deafening. Add on top of that personal Bible study, work, family, church, sleep, apps/games, books, and other creative pursuits (like keeping a blog), and it’s easy to feel this latent pressure to fit all of them in, and to do them perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Periodically, I have to do a “reset,” meaning I have to assess the things I’m working on and throw out what’s not important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, what matters most are the roles/activities that have eternal significance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jesus (personal)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Family&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Church (corporate)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then physical health:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleep&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exercise (which I don’t presently do)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking care of my family:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Education/Learning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bible Study&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reading Books&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Converting this into hours:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;table&quot;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sleep&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;56&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exercise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Work&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Commute&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Bible Study&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Church&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5+&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tfoot&gt;
&lt;/tfoot&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;118 / 168&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So those set times (including that pesky excercise I have yet to start) come out to about 70% of my week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, about 10-15 hours are wasted between the time I wake up at 4AM and start doing anything meaningful, like my Bible study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining 40-50 hours are for family and family activities, like practices.  They also include regular activities like eating and doing chores.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">If I’m not careful, life gets really complicated really fast. Just the noise of following the news can be deafening. Add on top of that personal Bible study, work, family, church, sleep, apps/games, books, and other creative pursuits (like keeping a blog), and it’s easy to feel this latent pressure to fit all of them in, and to do them perfectly.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sins of the Body</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/17/body.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sins of the Body" /><published>2019-05-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-05-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/05/17/body</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/17/body.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;...do you not know that your body is a temple of the Holy Spirit within you, whom you have from God? You are not your own, for you were bought with a price. So glorify God in your body. &lt;cite&gt;1 Cor 6:19-20&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I’m thinking about how we care for our bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Americans today are in extremely bad health.  We’re overweight, we smoke or vape, we drink, we don’t sleep.  We do all kinds of things that are bad for our health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christians are no exception to this rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a constant tension in our society over homosexuality, as though it is a special sin.  It definitely falls into what I would say is a certain category of sin, a sin against our own bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Flee from sexual immorality. Every other sin a person commits is outside the body, but the sexually immoral person sins against his own body.&quot;&lt;cite&gt;1 Cor 6:18&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, &lt;strong&gt;I think many more of us — including Christians — sin against our bodies by not taking care of ourselves&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-gift-from-god&quot;&gt;A Gift From God&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By simply giving us life, God has given us an immeasurably valuable gift.  Our bodies are a miracle in terms of sheer existence, of course, but also in the way they function.  Every system is fine-tuned so perfectly in order to sustain life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-precious-resource&quot;&gt;A Precious Resource&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These bodies are vehicles for us to use to praise God and to be the “hands and feet” of Jesus.  They are a tool, a resource that we have been given — just like money — to expand and deepen his kingdom in this world. And, just like the servants given talents to use for their master (Mat 25:14ff), we are given these bodies as a resource to increase what God has given us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our bodes are also a tool for praise.  We must “glorify God in [our] bodies.”  This means that we need to make God famous through how we are for ourselves.  How we care for ourselves makes a statement to others about our God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;temple-of-the-holy-spirit&quot;&gt;Temple of the Holy Spirit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our bodies are where the Holy Spirit is worshipped.  As such, it can be desecrated just as much as it can be sanctified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, just like any temple can be defiled by worshipping the wrong gods within it, our bodies can be defiled by what we put in it and do with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;license&quot;&gt;License&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;'Food is meant for the stomach and the stomach for food'&amp;mdash;and God will destroy both one and the other.&quot;&lt;cite&gt;1 Cor 6:13&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Corinth, people justified their excess by saying, “this is what our bodies were created for,” meaning that we were made to eat, so let’s eat as much as we can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul says that this is blatantly false, and that by misusing our bodies, they can and will be destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;'All things are lawful for me', but not all things are helpful.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People were using grace as a license for hedonism, as though just because something wasn’t explicitly prohibited, they could do whatever they wanted as much as they wanted.  Paul says that this license is limited by what is &lt;em&gt;beneficial&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul gives a qualification to our grace, meaning that we have freedom, as long as what we are doing is good for The Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overeating&quot;&gt;Overeating&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe being overweight is a sin.  Granted, this is not explicitly stated in the Bible, so I don’t hold everyone to it, but as I understand it, it’s damaging to this gift God has given me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our bodies were designed with a mechanism to store up energy.  We take advantage of that by eating diets of garbage, empty calories, and throwaway carbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we justify this because these things &lt;em&gt;taste good&lt;/em&gt;.  I don’t think this is any different than justifying sexual sin because it feels good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Phillipians, Paul speaks of “the enemies of the cross of Christ,” saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Their end is destruction, &lt;strong&gt;their god is their belly&lt;/strong&gt;, and they glory in their shame, with minds set on earthly things.&lt;cite&gt;Phil 3:19&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This statement means that they are ruled by their bodies and physical desires.  To put it another way, &lt;strong&gt;their cravings have become their god.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;neglecting-sleep&quot;&gt;Neglecting Sleep&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sleep is as integral to our life as eating, breathing, and reproducing.  All living things sleep.  It is where our bodies repair themselves, and to neglect sleep is to do great harm to ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our busy modern lives we work and play much harder than our bodies were designed for.  We &lt;em&gt;require&lt;/em&gt; eight hours of sleep a night, but an overwhelming majority of us get less than six.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a symptom of our desire for pleasure.  Whether we’re working or playing, we’re filling the short time we have with activities that get us what we want, even if it’s at a crappy job.  We’re working to get ahead in life.  We’re playing and relaxing to try to recharge after all of this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bible doesn’t mention a requirement to sleep, so once again, I don’t hold anyone else to this, but I believe that this chronic lack of sleep is a sin.  It is abusive to this resource God has given us, and we abuse it for our own sake, not God’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;alcohol-and-caffeine&quot;&gt;Alcohol and Caffeine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alcohol and caffeine are not required by out bodies to function, and are by and large harmful substances to our physical bodies.  Of course alcohol isn’t necessarily such, but it most often is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We put all kinds of substances into our bodies to help us either relax or work harder.  Caffeine is another example of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In moderation, these are often not harmful, but very, very easily they can be.  We must be careful with how we use them so they will not damage this gift God has given us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nicotine-and-drugs&quot;&gt;Nicotine and Drugs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nicotine and drugs are used to help us escape, to calm us down or help ease our minds.  They cool our anxiety, but they are damaging to our bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;escaping-idolatry&quot;&gt;Escaping Idolatry&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By letting our minds and bodies rule us, we place them on the throne of our lives and worship them in the place of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to remember that just like any other sin, sheer willpower will not deliver us from the sin of trashing out bodies, only turning to Jesus to be our savior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We must remember that we are not our own.  We were bought with a price, and that price was the life of Jesus.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="sin" /><category term="idolatry" /><summary type="html">...do you not know that your body is a temple of the Holy Spirit within you, whom you have from God? You are not your own, for you were bought with a price. So glorify God in your body. 1 Cor 6:19-20</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can We Keep God’s Law?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/12/can-we-keep-law.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can We Keep God’s Law?" /><published>2019-05-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-05-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/05/12/can-we-keep-law</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/12/can-we-keep-law.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;did-god-create-us-unable-to-keep-his-law&quot;&gt;Did God Create Us Unable to Keep His Law?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;No, but because of the disobedience of our first parents, Adam and Eve, all of creation is fallen; we are all born in sin and guilt, corrupt in our nature and unable to keep God's law.&lt;br /&gt;(New City Catechism)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;able-to-keep-the-law&quot;&gt;Able to Keep The Law&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam and Eve were created in God’s image.  When God created them, he said “It is very good.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sin-enters-humanity&quot;&gt;Sin Enters Humanity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When tempted by Satan, Adam and Eve chose to disobey, to declare themselves and their desires higher than God’s commands.  They believed that real freedom came from living by their own rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this, all of humanity fell.  All of their descendants inherited that corruption (Rom 5:12).  We died (Rom 5:15).  We are slaves to sin (Rom 6:16, 20).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have all gone astray.  We have all fallen short of the glory of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-role-of-the-law&quot;&gt;The Role of The Law&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Old Testament Law exists for one reason: To show us that we cannot live without sinning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;For by works of the law no human being will be justified in his sight, since through the law comes knowlewdge of sin.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;(Rom 3:20)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;radically-depraived&quot;&gt;Radically Depraived&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radically comes from the Latin &lt;em&gt;radix&lt;/em&gt;, meaning “at the core.”  We are not completely depraived (evil); we are able to do good things, and often do.  However, we are sinful at our core, in our hearts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why children don’t have to be taught how to lie or hit or be selfish.  It’s just natural to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-remedy&quot;&gt;The Remedy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are sinful, and God’s Law plainly shows us that.  Thankfully, just as death entered through one man, Jesus brings us life (Rom 5:17, 19).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;...as sin reigned in death, grace also might reign through righteousness leading to eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;(Rom 5:21)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though we’ve earned death through our sin, Jesus has bought us eternal life (Rom 6:23).  We are set free from our sin.  The curse has been broken!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="sin" /><category term="Romans" /><category term="catechism" /><summary type="html">Did God Create Us Unable to Keep His Law?</summary></entry></feed>